<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>In the yeare 59. in the fourth month, the last day of the month being the 5th day of the week</title>
            <author>Eccles, Solomon, 1618-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E128</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827829</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827829</idno>
            <idno type="VID">207628</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21541)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207628)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1924:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>In the yeare 59. in the fourth month, the last day of the month being the 5th day of the week</title>
                  <author>Eccles, Solomon, 1618-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for M. W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the 6th month, 1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Solomon Eccles.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Inner Light --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>English literature --  Quaker authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Experience (Religion) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:207628:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>In the yeare 59. in the fourth Month, the laſt day of the Month being the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of the Week.</head>
            <p>THE preſence of the Lord God was felt within me, and in his light he let me ſee what his pleaſure was with me; it was clearly ſhew'd me that I ſhould goe to the Steeplehouſe in <hi>Alderman-bury</hi> the firſt day of the week then following, and take with me ſomething to work, and doe it in the Pulpit at their ſinging time.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſight I found much unwillingneſſe in my ſelfe, yet ſitting ſtill with trembling, there came upon me a very great weight preſſing me to obedience; yea a heavy burthen was felt, till I had conſented to obey; I felt the weight to increaſe, oh how hard my unwilling will was to yeild, but the Lord ſtrengthened me, and having conſented, I found a little eaſe, yea I did reſolve in the power of the Lord to goe on: I purpoſed to carry with me a Pocket to ſow.</p>
            <p>So the firſt day morning being the <hi>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
               </hi> day of the <hi>5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> month after the <hi>8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> hour one of the Doers being open, I paſſed in, thinking to get into the Pulpit to hide my ſelfe there till their ſinging time, and then get up and work; The Sexton ſpying me, took me by the arme, ſaid friend we doe not open yet, for it was their Communion day as they call: but the time I was in, I found that the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries were higher then the Pulpit, and I ſhould have been diſcovered before their ſong began; I ſee the Clark giving Tickets: ſoe about the <hi>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> hour their Dores were opened, I paſſed in as one of their owne crowd, the throng came in very faſt, I gat into one of the Galleries to ſpye if poſſible to get in the Pulpit ſome way, but I found none at that time, ſo they began to read, and I came downe, and finding no way to get into the Pulpit, I came to the Table that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for that troop, I thought to get upon the Table to worke, but the Table was ſet round with young men, and when they began their ſong, they laid on their hats upon the Table, ſo I ſtanding ſtill waiting on the Lord, having a great mind to doe the Lords work; their ſong being up, my hat offended them, they took it off, and caſt it away, and one of the young men gave it me again, I put it on, and it offended again, in ſo much that Piercefall did perceive me, who came violently, and tooke my hat off to flng it away, but I held it, then he tooke me by the hair of the head, and drag'd me out, and as one of their own company teſtified to his face that he ſtroke me, but I cannot ſay that, but a luſty red hair'd man
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:207628:2"/> did ſtrike me, I ſuppoſed him to be an officer in that hatefull place, but Pierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall after he had drag'd me out by the haire, ſaid Sarrah doe you not know Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Duike, I ſaid nay, for I did not know him; Sorrah ſaid he, I put him in priſon, and finde him ten pound, and you muſt be ſerved ſo to, and ſo charg'd the Conſtable with me, and went himſelfe in again, and received the Sacrament for all this.</p>
            <p>The Conſtable told me that I might goe away if I would, but in againe I muſt not. So I ſtood a while and finding in my ſelfe no conſtraint, I paſſed away to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards More fields finding a little eaſe from the weight of the burden, being faithfull to what might be done at that time: but the <hi>6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> day of the weeke being the <hi>8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> day of the moneth ſitting at worke in my Shop but not on the Shop-board, the burden of the Lord came upon me, and the light making mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the ſame thing that was not yet done, muſt be done, and the Lord would not diſcharge me, but laid a neceſſity upon me. I beholding this with trembling and feare; I did reſolve in the power of the Lord not to eat nor drink, till I had performed the Lords requiring. So having purpoſed in heart, I greatly deſired the Lords aſſiſtance; and it was ſhewed me how to doe it, and the Lord made way for me.</p>
            <p>So the firſt day of the week being the <hi>10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> day of the <hi>5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> moneth, I waited opportunity till the ſinging time began, which when I heard, I paſſed in, but being fearefull to he taken with the hat againe; and ſo looſe my maine buſineſſe, for the Lord: I ſtept out againe, but ſtaid not, I came in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; I lookt towards the Pulpit and ſpyed the pue dore open, that the Preiſt might p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe up the Pulpit. So I waited thinking that <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund Calomy</hi> would goe up the Pulpit, I intended to get in before him; for thought I that boy that ſits upon the ſtairs will open the Pulpit dore for the Prieſt, and I'le get in before, but no Prieſt came, whereupon in the power of the Lord; I fixed my eye upon the Pulpit, and I ſpyed and iron hooke, and I paſſed through the pue up the ſtairs, and unhookt the dore, and pull'd twice and gat it open, and I ſat my ſelfe down upon the Cuſhin, and my feet upon the ſeate where the Prieſt when he hath told out his lyes doth ſit downe, and having my work ready, I pull'd one or two ſtitches. The people loſt their ſong, and ſome cried pull him downe, ſome breake his neck downe, and a luſty fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low came up and did intend to doe me a miſchiefe, and rang my neck as if he would have rung it in two. Soe I let goe my hold and he flang me downe ſtairs; but the Lord preſerved me, and I felt no hurt; for having done that which the Lord required me to doe I was full of peace; and it had been little to me if they had there taken away or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:207628:2"/> kil'd the body. For I was full of joy, and they were full of wroth and madneſſe; ſo they tore my Coat off and my hat, and draged me out, and one took me by the haire and flung me upon the ground, and ſome that was without ſaid why do you uſe the man ſo, but I gat up again, then they draged me quite out into the ſtreet, and there held me, and while they held me, one came, and gave me a violent kick on the ſhins, and ſaid he could find in his heart to knock me down, he made my ſhin bleed, and another kickt me on the other ſhin, but did not much hurt, another ſaid that I had beene ſome notorious ſinner heretoſore and now came to doe ſomething that might merit, Preſently the Church-warden as they call him, came out, and he and the Bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toler carried me away to the Counter till their Sermon was ended, as they call it, then they carried me away to <hi>Pauls</hi> Yard to ſtay for the Mayor, but the Sargent ſaid he would carry me away to the Mayors Houſe and there ſtay me till he came in; ſo he did: And all the way through <hi>Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſter-Row</hi> as I went, the boys kickt my heels, ſo then the Mayor came in, and they told him that I was at work in the Pulpit; then ſaid he to me, Wherefore did you work there? I ſaid in obedience to the Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: he ſaid, It was a falſe Spirit, and ſaid he, Where are your ſureties? I ſaid The Lord was my ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; he ſaid, The Lord would not beare me out in this thing: ſaid he to them, Carry him againe to the Counter: So they carried me back agine, and there I was till the third day.</p>
            <p>Now let all ſober people judge whither I did this thing out of envy againſt either Prieſt or People.</p>
            <p>Yea farther I ſay, the Lord God lay it not to their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:207628:3"/> charge, who have ſaid that I did it in malice, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſhneſſe, and envy; it is the deſire of my ſoul that they might be ſaved.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>And ſo do write my name being a Priſoner for the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the Lord in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Goal in Newgate <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi> Committed <date>the 15th. of the 5th. Moneth 59.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Solomon Eccles.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for M. W. in the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Month, 1659.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:207628:3"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
